Albert Van Dusen Papers
© 2010 University of Connecticut
Albert Van Dusen Papers
undated,
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Van Dusen, Albert
linear feet
MSS19940071
Biography
Published Works:
,,.
,,.
Scope and Content
Arrangement
( )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to [children's literature and associated artwork, nursing education and leadership, literature, various aspects of Connecticut history, the experiences of Connecticut residents while in the military, alternative lifestyles, politics and publications, Connecticut labor, Connecticut nursing education, New England railroad, Connecticut business records, Connecticut's ethnic communities, Connecticut's flora, fauna and environment, Connecticut politics, the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students, etc.]. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Dodd
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
xxx
Organizations:
xxx
Family Names:
xxx
Places:
xxx
Subjects:
xxx
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Blueprints.; Maps.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Minutes.; Diaries.; Press releases.; Charms.; School Records.; Uniforms.; Dolls.; Artwork.; Videocassettes.; Audio cassettes.; Audio visual materials.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Illustrations.; Manuscripts.; Galley proofs.; Typescripts.; Photocopies.; Notes.; Motion picture film.; Books.; Scrap-Books.; Stuffed toys.; Interviews.; Oral Histories.; Lawsuits.; Engravings.; Sketches.; Drawings.; Speeches.; Obituaries.; Resolutions.; Petitions.; Posters.; Patents.; Albums.; Underground comics.; Contracts.; Sound recordings.; Poems.; Bylaws.; Newsletters.; Newspapers.; Recipes.; Lantern slides.; Microfilm.; Filmstrips.; Histories.; Abstracts.; Examinations.; Broadsides.; Patterns.; Swatches.; Leases.; Plats.; Deeds.; Field notes.; Catalogs.; Advertisements.
Occupations:
xxx
Functions:
xxx
Titles:
xxx
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Detailed Description
- Inventory, undated
  - Correspondence, undated, 1957-1977 (Box 1)
    Correspondence regarding speaking engagements at various Historical Societies broken down by state. These states include Maine, Massachusetts, New Hampshire, Rhode Island and Vermont. Other correspondence includes travel arrangements, grant proposals and workshops. There is also correspondence with the AASLH including candidates nominated, awards recieved and general committee communication.
  - Personal and professional files, undated, 1968-1980
    This box contains files listed alphabetically A-C
    - Correspondence with individuals with last name begining with A. Correspondence with Historical societies begining with A, inquiring information about Jonathan Trumbull and Abbreviations used in printing. (Box 2:, Folder 1-2)
    - American Antiquarian Society. Inventory of collection with attention to Jonathan Trumbull papers. (Box 2:, Folder 3)
    - Analysis of Jonathan Trumbull papers by Van Dusen (Box 2:, Folder 4-11)
    - Analysis of Trumbull papers from Various archives and libraries including the Connecticut archives and the colonial war archives. These files also contain rules and regulations for documentary editing. (Box 2:, Folder 12-20)
    - Correspondece with various individuals, historical societies and libraries about any Jonathan Trumbull papers. (Box 2:, Folder 21-23)
    - Correspondence about Trumbull papers and an announcement for a public auction on November 5, 1975 where Trumbull items were auctioned off. (Box 2:, Folder 24-25)
    - Outline of Volume one of Jonathan Trumbull papers, including letters to and from Trumbull, notebooks and sermons. Also chronology of Trumbull's life, 1710-1766. (Box 2:, Folder 26-27)
    - bindery instructions. Also a request for Van Dusen to submit Jonathan Trumbull project plans to BINET. (Box 2:, Folder 28-29)
    - Information about Trumbull House. Biographical information about Van Dusen requested by various magazines. (Box 2:, Folder 30-31)
    - Correspondence with historical societies and libraries about Trumbull papers. (Box 2:, Folder 32-34)
    - Chronolgy of Trumbull's life, 1730-1785 (Box 2:, Folder 35-38)
    - Correspondence about Trumbull papers. (Box 2:, Folder 39-40)
  - Correspondence, undated, 1968-1980 (Box 3)
    This box contains correspondence between Van Dusen and various Historical societies, libraries and colleges about trumbull papers in the U.S as well as Europe. Also there are records of grant proposals and grants recieved for the Jonathan Trumbull project.
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
  - Correspondence and other works, Undated, 1961-1978 (Box 4)
    The first half of the box is correspondence with various historical societies and libraires reguarding Trumbull papers. Also records reguarding the Trumbull papers project funding.The second half of the box contains printings, works cited and indexes from Van Dusen's book Connecticut published in 1961. Also the book The Public Records of the State of Connecticut May 1800-October 1801 By Albert and Wilda Van Dusen published 1965. This is not a bound copy and the book is broken down into sections, including appendixes, which are also continued into the next box.
    - Correspondence and other works, Undated, 1961-1981 (Box 5)
      This box contains illustration credits, indexs,radom house captions and four incomplete copies of Van Dusen's book Connecticut. Also a copy of Albert and Wilda Van Dusen's book The Public Records of the State of Connecticut May 1800-October 1801. There are two copies of copies of Connecticut records used in this publication. Pictures, newspaper clippings and few photocopied documents on Jonathan Trumbull are also in this box.The last part of the box contins personal papers from Dusen's teaching years at The University of Connecticut. Included is a syllabus for each class, grades, student evaluations, papers, student correspondence and exam sheets.
    - Correspondence and personal papers, Undated, 1953-1980 (Box 6)
      Classes taught by Van Dusen including a syllabus for each class, grades, student evaluations, student papers and exam sheets. This box also contains papers about Samuel Russell and company used for the paper written by Van Dusen entitled Samuel Russell and the China Trade 1818-1831. History department meetings with minutes, correspondence with AASLH regarding grant proposals and multiple folders on the NAMES committeeas well as the Oral History advisory committee.
    - Note Cards, Undated (Box 7)
      Box of note cards (some hand written some typed)Broken down into several sections including Biography, general works, local, manuscripts, account books, monographs, newpapers/periodicals, printed sources, travel, tercentenary publications/pamphlets and a large section on middletown. All other cards are mostly from and about Connecticut with a few others from other New England areas.
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
    - 
  - Jonathan Trumbull correspondence
    Photostatic copies of correspondence, legal documents and legislative materials associated with Jonathan Trumbull are arranged chronologically within large envelopes. Envelopes may also contain photocopies and transcriptions. Manuscript notations by Van Dusen occasionally recorded on envelopes.
    - 1770 - 1772 May (Box 8)
    - 1772 June - 1774 April 21 (Box 9)
    - 1774 April 25 - 1775 May 31 (Box 10)
    - 1775 June 1 - 1775 (Box 11)
      Correspondents include CT delegates, Benedict Arnold, and John Hancock.
    - 1775 October 13 - 1776 April 1 (Box 12)
      Correspondents include John Hancock and General George Washington regarding impending trial.
    - 1776 April 2 - 1776 August 11 (Box 13)
      General correspondence plus letters to General Assembly regarding manufacturing of Sulphur (May), Naval Officers (May), procuring money (May), sending militia, exc.
    - 1776 August 12 - 1776 December 16 (Box 14)
    - 1776 December 17 - 1776 March 31 (Box 15)
    - 1777 April 11 - 1777 July 11 (Box 16)
    - 1777 July 12 - 1777 October 8 (Box 17)
    - 1777 October 9 - 1778 January 23 (Box 18)
    - 1778 January 24 - 1778 August 31 (Box 19)
    - 1778 September 3 - 1779 March 1 (Box 20)
    - 1779 March 2 - 1779 July 9 (Box 21)
    - 1779 July 10 - 1779 September 8 (Box 22)
    - 1779 September 9 - 1780 February 9 (Box 23)
    - 1780 February 10 - 1780 June 8 (Box 24)
    - 1780 June 9 - 1780 August 15 (Box 25)
    - 1780 August 17 - 1780 November 19 (Box 26)
    - 1780 November 20 - 1781 March 2 (Box 27)
    - 1781 March 3 - 1781 June 12 (Box 28)
    - 1781 June 20 - 1781 September 29 (Box 29)
    - 1781 October 1 - 1782 April 30 (Box 30)
      A document entitled "James Austins Confessions on illicit trade (November 29, 1781) received folder note by Van Dusen
    - 1782 May 1 - 1782 November 8 (Box 31)
    - 1782 November 9 - 1783 October 1 (Box 32)
    - 1783 October 2 - 1800 January 15 (Box 33)
    - 1724 - 1785 (Box 34)
      Collection of Van Dusen's notes on Jonathan Trumbull's sermons from 1724 to 1785. Photocopies of the transcripts are included. Examples in collection include J.T's reflections on becoming a minister followed by notes by Van Dusen. J.T's commonplace book followed by notes from Van Dusen. Correspondence, letters, ledgers, account books, J.T's confession of faith. a "Free Status Certificate" for a slave, and J.T's "Mulatto Girl Grace.
    - 1752 - 1755 (1744 was added towards end of the set) (Box 35)
      misc. correspondence and items including General Assembly Response to the Albany Plan of Union.
    - 1758 - 1763 (Box 36)
      Misc. correspondence and inventories concerning foodstuffs and merchandise
    - 1762 - 1765 (Box 37)
      Misc correspondence and notes. Box contains some duplicates.
    - Note Cards, Undated, 1960 (Box 38)
      The label on the original box reads Rel-Town TKT (N.H). This box contains a samll part of a very large index. The entire index is typed in a list and is located in the front of the box. The box goes from religion to towns.
    - Note Cards, Undated (Box 39)
      Lable on the Origianl box reads Bibligraphy Connecticut cards. This is a typed up list of Dusen's Book Connceticut each individual source used in the book is typed on its own note card. There are some note cards that are labled omitted from final draft and are placed at the back.
    - Note Cards, Undated (Box 40)
      Box containing information about the life of Samuel Huntingtonof Norwich, Connecticut. Includes Huntington's correspondence between 1731-1796, information about his family house in scotland. Also Van Dusen's correspondence with various historical societies and libraries looking for information about Huntington.
    - Note Cards, undated (Box 41)
      The label on this box reads, Connecticut State Libraries towns A-N. The box contains information on town celebrations, famous individuals and information on churches.
    - Note Cards, Undated (Box 42)
      The label on this box reads, Connecticut State Libraries towns O-Z. The box contains information on town celebrations, famous individuals and information on churches.
    - Note Cards, 1924-1935 (Box 43)
      The Label on the box reads Hartford Courant and Hartford Times There is a note card in the front of the box listing all other newspapers used including the Bridgeport Times-star The Meriden Record The New Haven Register The New London Day The Stamford Advocate The Torrington Register and the Waterburg Republican The two main categories in this box are politics and economics, each with several sub sections.
    - Note Cards, Undated (Box 44)
      The label on this box reads Index A. This box contains an index used for a book or a series of articles listed A-Y. It contains a list of people and towns (mostly Connecticut) with several cards about Jonathan Trumbull.
    - Note Cards, Undated (Box 45)
      This box contains Note Cards on Connecticut including sections on religion, politics, foreign correspondence between various individuals. Many cards have the Hartford Courant as a source.
    - Note Cards, 1914-1922 (Box 46)
      This box contains information on the 1914-1922 elections. The note cards are broken down into several sections including WWI, Womens suffrage, state legislation, politics, prohibition, Ku Klux Klan, book burning and labor.
    - Note Cards, 1800-1935 (Box 47)
      Information on Politics (1800-1935). most sources from the Hartford Courant and the Hartford Times
    - Note Cards, 1936-~1962 (Box 48)
      Note cards with information on politics(between 1936-~1962) most sources from the Hartford Courant
    - personal and professional papers, 1940's-1970's,undated (Box 49)
      Corresondense between Van Dusen and various musuems including committee meetings, staff meetings(for Uconn) invitations to various events, newsletters, newspaper clippings and personal letters between friends. This box also contains notes on the entire first draft of the play With Sword and Palette: A Spectacle Drama on Patriot-Artist John Turmbull Also letters of correspondce between Samuel Russell and various individuals (a great deal with his brother A.E Russell) for the paper Samuel Russell and the China Trade, 1818-1831 The last part of the box contains personal information about Wilda's past including diplomas, old school work, replys to her and Albert's wedding invitations, old pictures, dress patterns and an article in the Durham Morning Herald announcing Wilda and Albert's wedding with a picture of Wilda in her wedding gown.
    - 1763 - 1789, 1784 - 1785, 1781 - 1783 (Box 50)
      Photostats of Conn. Archives, Rev War: volume 28 (part 1,2), 29, 30, 25 (part 2). Washington Papers microfilm reel 33, 34. (typed and original list)
    - dates include 1781 - 1783, 1777 - 1778 (Box 51)
      Microprints of John Trumbull Papers from New Hampshire Records and Archives (further identification on back of each microprint). Photostats of Conn. Archives Rev War-- first series vol. 25, 33 (part 1). (typed and original list included)
    - 1675 - 1775, 1758 (Box 52)
      Phototstats of Conn. Archives, Rev. War: colonial vol. 7 (part 2). 1758 (part 2) (typed and original list included)
  - Unidentified photostats, undated (Box 53)
    "cardboards 2"
  - Unidentified photostats, undated (Box 54)
    "cardboards 3"
  - Unidentified photostats, undated (Box 55)
    "cardboards 4"
  - 1631 - 1784, 1766 - 1771, 1776 August 29 - 1776 Novemember 30 (Box 56)
    Photostats of Connecticut Colonial Official Trumbull Papers (1631 - 1784), vol. 30. Letterbook (1766-1771). Photostats of Conn. Archives, Rev. War Series 1, vol. 31, Cart 1: Soldiers, vessels, letters, grievances. Microcopies of the George Washington Papers, reel 39, 38 (August 29 - November 30, 1776 (original list plus further identification on back of each microcopy)
  - 1780, 1776 - 1777 (Box 57)
    "Historical Magazine items copied" - votes for November (1780). Vol XXIX TP 1776 - 1777
  - Dates include 1774 - 1789, 1775 - 1789 (Box 58)
    Microcopies of the National Archives, Roll 80: copies of the continental congress 1774 - 1789, Connecticut State copies 1775 - 1779, vol. 2 (title page include, original list included with vol. 1). Microcopies of the National Archives 247, Roll 80, copies of Continental Congress 1774 - 1789, Connecticut State copies 1775 - 1789, vol. 1 (duplicates although one appears to be handwritten and the other typed).
  - 1782 (Box 59)
    Photostats of Connecticut Archives Revolutionary War. Vol. 23, 1782 records (photocopied list of dated documents).
  - (Box 60)
    Photocopies of microprints of Trumbull Documents from the national archive. Entitled "complete reel to be copied"-- further identification of each frame on front of each copy, no original list included, numerical order of each frame listed only. Microcopies of the National Archives "microcopy 247", roll 24, items 14, 15, 16; copies of Continental Congress 1774 - 1789 (notes and original list included). Microcopies of the Papers Of Eleazer Wheelock, reel 1,2,3,8,9,10,11: June 18, 1755 - June 3, 1776 (typed document identification and original list). Microcopies of Public Record Office- War Office: V34:28, 1758 - 1763 (Copies not in numerical order but in the order as listed on original list)
  - Dates include: 1753 - 1775, 1778 - 1779, 1775 - 1779 (Box 61)
    Box contains photocopies of Connecticut Colonial Office, Trumbull copies vol. 28, 27, 26. Letter noted to be pre-1769. Letter book 1 (1775 - 1778), 2 (1778 - 1779), and 3 (1753 - 1775).
  - (Box 62)
    Connecticut Archives First Series - Misc. vol. 3, Cart 2 1685 - 1789 (original and typed list). Connecticut Archives photocopies series 2, vol 3 and 4. Goup of zerozed copies of items from Yale library (Trumbull related documents). Photostats from Massachusets Historical Society (original list). PRO material from Connecticut Historical Society relating to Glen Curgenven (check spelling) and New Haven customers. Connecticut Historical Society, Ames, Almanac, Lebanon survey notes. Connecticut Archives "Colonial Wars" vol. 5 pt. 1 and 2. Horse Guards Charter. Photostats from CT Archives: Insolvent Debtors vol. 1 (1762 - 1787), civil offices vol. 2 (1725 - 1742), colleges and schools series 1 (1661 - 1789), finances and currency vol. 2 (1725 - 1737), colonial boundaries vol. 3 (1670 - 1827), crimes misdeameanors series 1, vol. 4 (1737 - 1755), finances and currency series 1, vol. 5 (1764 - 1789), foreign correspondence vol. 1, cart 2 (1663 - 1748). Colonial War vol. 4, pt. 2, vol. 10, part 1.
  - (Box 63)
    Microprints of George Washinton Papers series 4: reel 41 (April - May 1777), 42 (30 May 1777 - 22 July 1777), 45 (26 October 1777 - 3 December 1777), 44 (4 September 1777 - 24 October 1777), 43 (23 July 1777 - 3 September 1777).
  - (Box 64)
    Connecticut Archives: First Series (militia) vol 4 (1747 - 1752), vol 5 (1752 - 1757), vol 2 (1730 - 1740), vol 3 cart 1 (1635 - 1789). Second Series vol 55 (1770 - 1856), vol 56 (1774 - 1834), vol 16 (1784 - 1788), vol 6 (1769). Third Series vol 3 (1728 - 1790). Trumbull Papers vol 12, cart 2 (1631 - 1784..1780). Trade and Maritime vol 1, cart 2 first series (1668 - 1789). Connecticut Archives 1st series, ecclesiastical vol 6 (1737 - 1742) and vol 7 (1742 - 1745). Colonial Wars vol 6 (1675 - 1775) and vol 7. 1st series (travel) vol 3 (1770 - 1788). Towns and Lauds vol 8- cart 1 (1629 - 1789), vol 7- cart 1 and 2, vol 3 (1742 - 1754), vol 5 (1763), vol 9. Microcopy of reel 16 (Henry Capers) June 22, 1779. Connecticut Colonial Office: Trumbull Capers vol 4, cart 2 (1631 - 1784). Capers of Continental Congress. Capers relating to claims of territory for Pennsylvania and Connecticut, Continental Congress (microcopy 247, roll no. 89). Henry Capres 1777 - 1779, roll 7 and 9. Microcopy 247, roll 23 (letterbooks of president of congress September 15, 1775 and December 8, 1778). Washington Capers vol. 10, 11, 12, 7, 8, 9, 10. Trumbull documents from National Archives. Photocopies of Trumbull documents
  - Dates include: 1763, 1752 - 1756, 7 December 1763 - 22 January 1765 (Box 65)
    General Correspondence between Trumbull and associates. Photocopied, typed, and handwritten transcripts included. Dates in box are out of order: first set ends on 12 October 1763, second begins on 7 December 1763 and goes through 1764.
  - Dates include: 23 December 1765 - 1766, 1767 -1768, 1769 (Box 66)
    General correspondence, court cases, summons, etc. Dates also slightly out of order.
  - Dates include: 1723 - 1724, 1738 up to 1785 (Box 67)
    Correspondence, sermon notes, deeds, commonplace books, records, notes on court cases, exc.
  - 30 April 1760 - 17 September 1770 (Box 68)
    correspondence, random documents (school covenant, receipts, General Assembly reports).
  - (Box 69)
    Begins with packet containing information and biographies on notable colonial figures. Assembled alphabetically beginning with A (Ethan Allen, Samuel Adams, exc.). Boxes also includes items of interest and background not related to Trumbull, various documents (photostats) under the title "documents for editing", and correspondence both unrelated and related to J. Trumbull.
  - Date range is as early as 1759 and as late as 1789. (Box 70)
    Correspondence, "act book" containing records of purchases and inventory list, and confessions of faith. Box also includes two large black ledges entitled "Led I 1757 - 1771" and "Led A 1759 - 1774"
  - Dates include: 3 August 1761, 19 April 1764, 1764, 1757, 1754, 1765, 1772, 1763, exc. (Box 71)
    Correspondence, manuscripts (typed and photocopied) of Trumbull's sermons and sermon notes. Box also includes bills of change and account books.
  - (Box 72)
    Photostat copies of misc. papers. Microfilm copies of presidential papers (George Washington Papers), French and Indian War documents, items from Trumbull Papers Collections
  - 4 November 1754 - 20 October 1756 (Box 73)
    Correspondence and two rolled up photostats.
  - (Box 74)
    Contains ledges E, F, F duplicate, and G.
  - (Box 75)
    Ledgers.
  - (Box 76)
    Spanish Ship Case Papers (photostats), Spanish Case misc. problems (correspondence, Trumbull report to General Assembly concerning Spanish Ship Case).
  - Dates below (Box 77)
    Ledger A 1759 - 1762, A pt. 2 1766 - 1775, L 1760 - 1766, K 1757 - 1760, H 1752 - 1753
  - 18 August 1752 - 30 October 1754 (Box 78)
    Correspondence.
  - (Box 79)
    Photostats from Connecticut Archives - Revolutionary War First Series. Content similiar to that of boxes 59 - 64.
  - (Box 80)
    Library budget request, folders containing budget and finance documents, annual reports, exc.
  - (Box 81)
    Personal possessions: catalogs, magazines, newspaper clippings, misc. papers.
  - (Box 82)
    Financial papers and typed letters concerning funding of Trumbull Papers Project. Funding and research proposals.
  - (Box 83)
    Collection of Bicentennial Series "American Revolution Bicentennial Comission" booklets: 1 - 35, 8 and 11 are missing.
  - (Box 84)
    Misc. papers including: notes, letters, table of contents from Trumbull Papers. Bundles of notecards with notes and addresses on them. Folders containing pictures, notes, photocopies.
  - 21 December 1752 - 31 August 1767 (Box 85)
    Trumbull correspondence (typed transcripts and photocopies)
  - 15 Febuary 1749/50 - 20 August 1750 (Box 86)
    Correspondence (photostats and photocopies)
  - 6 October 1761 - 29 Febuary/ 2 March 1764 (Box 87)
    Correspondence. Dates are out of order.
  - January/Febuary 1757 - 25 December 1758 (Box 88)
    Correspondence
  - Dates include: January 1744 - 25 January 1749/50 - July 1784 (Box 89)
    Correspondence, confessions of faith, lebanon school covenant, exc.
  - 1737 - 18 July 1746 - 1747 (Box 90)
    Court cases, summons, probate court.
  - Dates include: September 1755 - 7 June 1771 - 3 September 1755 - 25 May 1758. (Box 91)
    Correspondence, probate court cases, summons, genereal assembly matters, acts, motions, and misc. documents.
  - Dates include: 19 June 1759, 11 Dec 1759, 12 January 1760 - 4 August 1760 (Box 92)
    Correspondence (typed, photostats, photocopies, transcripts, notes)
  - 1746 - 1752 (Box 93)
    Summons, orders of payment, correspondence, Trumbull sermon notes.
  - Dates include: 1723/24 - 1785, 1 July 1730 - 4 September 1730 - 24 December 1759 (Box 94)